let's find a formula for the sum a plus
ax plus ax squared up to ax to the K
minus 1 where X is greater than 1 a is a
positive number and K is a positive
integer we can make sense of this sum by
considering a line with lengths marked
at 1 x x squared x cubed and so on up to
x to the k then we can draw a
perpendicular line and start to build a
sequence of rectangles of width a over x
minus one the first rectangle has area a
the next rectangle has area ax the next
rectangle has an area of ax squared and
so on all the way until the last
rectangle which has an area of a x to
the K minus 1. so the total shaded area
in this rectangle is the finite sum
we're interested in but we can also just
compute the area of the rectangle in
terms of its endpoints we see the
rectangle has a length of x to the K
minus 1 so that the area enclosed is a
times x to the K minus a divided by x
minus 1. by Computing the area of this
rectangle in two separate ways we've
produced a formula for a finite
geometric sum